<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vox charitatis: containing a louder cry for bowels of compassion, to the Lord's poor afflicted people. : With a word of counsel and comfort to them, and a concluding word to their oppressors. / By A true lover of His truly Sacred Majesty, and all his faithful subjects.</title>
            <author>True lover of His truly Sacred Majesty.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96022</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V712A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186078</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077741</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077741</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151855</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96022)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151855)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2279:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vox charitatis: containing a louder cry for bowels of compassion, to the Lord's poor afflicted people. : With a word of counsel and comfort to them, and a concluding word to their oppressors. / By A true lover of His truly Sacred Majesty, and all his faithful subjects.</title>
                  <author>True lover of His truly Sacred Majesty.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 3-16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped with print show-through and some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library, Chicago, Illinois.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poverty --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151855:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>VOX CHARITATIS:</hi> CONTAINING A LOUDER CRY For Bowels of Compaſſion, to the Lord's Poor Afflicted People.</p>
            <p>With a Word of COUNSEL and COMFORT to Them; and a Concluding Word to their OPPRESSORS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a true lover of His truly Sacred Majeſty, and all his Faithful Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Open thy Mouth for the Dumb, in the Cauſe of all ſuch as are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to Deſtruction. Open thy Mouth, Judge Righteouſly, and plead the Cauſe of the Poor and Needy,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 31.8, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Turn ye unto him from whom the Children of Iſrael have deeply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa 31.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Lord, when thy hand is lifted up, they will not ſee; but they ſhall ſee, and be aſhamed for their envy towards thy People: yea, the Fire of thine Enemy ſhall devour them,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa 26.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151855:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151855:2"/>
            <head>VOX CHARITATIS: <hi>Containing a louder Cry, for Bowels of Compaſſion to the Lords Poor Afflicted People.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are informed by the Lord, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7. that it will not be as we ſhew; <hi>but as we ſow, ſo ſhall we reap:</hi> and in the ſecond and third verſe, are eſteemed nothing, if we bear not one anothers Burdens; that is to ſay, If we feel them not, as if they were on our ſelves, to help to make them light and eaſie to him on whom they are; by putting under our helping hand, to enable him to bear them; not knowing how ſoon our ſelves alſo (who are in the Body) <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.3. may have our own burthen, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.5. and need the helping hand of others; and as a Concluſion, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. we are required <hi>to do good to all, eſpecially the Houſhold of Faith.</hi> And indeed, <hi>Job</hi> eſteemed his Friends <hi>nothing, that ſaw his caſting down, and were afraid,</hi> Job 6.21. <hi>or were not aſhamed to make themſelves ſtrange to him,</hi> Job 19.3. Now regard to the Poor (eſpecially the poor of God's People) is required, with more plenty of Promiſes, and upon more perils in the neglect thereof, than any act of a Chriſtian beſides; and the Lord's diſtreſſed Ones, are called <hi>His Poor, Pſalm.</hi> 72.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 74.19. He ſtiles himſelf (in eſpecial manner) <hi>The Father of the Poor, the Widdow, and Fatherleſs, in his Holy Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Pſal.</hi> 98.5. and hath eſpouſed their cry, eſpecially in caſes of wrong, or neglect of them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.22, 23. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.49.—And indeed, the People of the Lord eſpecially, are in this day expoſed to greateſt poverty, by wayes ſcarce heard of; in a Land where Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs was pretended, but as when there was <hi>no King in Iſrael, Judg.</hi> 17.6. And as in all times (for many Reaſons) they ought to have the preference in Chriſtian Alms before any, ſo in this day more than ever; for other poor as they have latitudes in their Nature, ſo have opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities now to attend at the door of the belly-gods, who now abound
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151855:3"/>(as <hi>Sodom</hi>) in their ſenſual Feſtivals; and ſuch poor are now (many of them) transformed into Scullions, Players, Singing-boyes, Prieſts, Sub-Prieſts, Parators, Informers, Jaylers, Trapanners, and ſuch like retinue: Others of them alſo, having generally their liberty of getting their lively-hoods, as their more civil Genius may incline; which latter ſort (whoſe honeſt Callings may not yet with the utmoſt labour obtain a lively-hood) as they are alſo the Subjects of Chriſtian Charity; ſo they either have or can claim, and have the advantage of thoſe conſtant Pariſh Impoſitions, Publick Collections and Allowances for the Poor, throughout the Land, which the Lords Poor, are moſt of them (beyond their Ability) compel'd to pay to, and few of them (how poor ſoever) are ſharers of; beſides, the other poor (in extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Caſe) can have their Briefs, Admiſſions of their Widows and Fatherleſs into Schools and Hoſpitals, and other ſpecial Donations: But, who ſees not the Lords Poor broken in pieces, and driven from their former Callings, and comfortable Societies (wherein they were cared for and ſupported) without the helps aforeſaid; now under the evil eye of almoſt any evil Beaſt in all the Land: And who is ſo much a ſtranger in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as not to ſee that any of the other poor crew afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or others (how prophane or inconſiderable ſoever) may malice his poor Neighbour (who feareth the Lord, by almoſt any impertinent information) into the Goal? where then his Calling is interrupted; and what ever his poor Family ſuffers at home, the mind of his hungry Goaler muſt be fed, with more in a week by Fees and Uſury, for his poor Diet and Lodging, than perhaps he knew how to get for his Wife and Children in a Moneth before; and it may be ſix moneths there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he may be heard, and ſo doubtly robbed, both of his Calling, and the little Meal he had in the Barrel; Yea, perhaps when heard, he appears before ſuch cruel Judges, as ſhall ſtrengthen his Chain (though he be cleared in the Matter whereof he was firſt accuſed) if he anſwer not their humour, to ſome Abſurd, Illegal, Extemporary Queſtion, in the Breaſt, either of the unjuſt Judge, or by means of any malitious Juſtice, or ſtander by, though the firſt falſe Informer againſt him, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Have you taken the Oath of Obedience? What Church are you of? Are you a fifth Monarchy-man? Will you leave Preaching, or going to Meetings, or the like? Or if he be releaſed, perhaps he hath no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſetled himſelf again to his honeſt Calling, but is in like cruel man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner interrupted, to the loſs of his cuſtom, and diſcouragement of him to ſettle, if he ſhould be delivered; neither can he conſcientiouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Servant, or any Maſter ſo comfortably imploy or depend upon him; becauſe perhaps at the next Meeting to Worſhip his God (which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151855:3"/>is deſervedly dearer to him than his Life) he is again ſnatched from the Affairs depending upon him, which are then all at a ſtand. And for proof of theſe intollerable Sufferings of the Lords poor People, <hi>London</hi> it ſelf may be a looking-glaſs into the Land; and by it, you may gueſs <hi>How the dark places of the Earth, are full of the Habitations of Cruelty, Pſalm.</hi> 74.20. When in the chief City, even under the eye of the Chief, the imperious inſolencies of ſome are ſuch, and ſo boundleſſe, that many thouſand Families, its thought, have been brought to beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery hereby. And many have deſerted their Vocations, as thinking themſelves moſt unhappy, to have ſerved ſeven years, to be free of little in the chief City of the Land, but ſlavery to Subjects: Left now ſo free, in abſurd and boundleſs inſolency, by which, ſtill poverty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth, and the cry of the poor oppreſſed ones, as it <hi>goeth up daily before God,</hi> ſo it ſhould enter into our Souls; for God hath ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us, and we know not how evil the day may be, and therefore ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 11.2. <hi>Give a Portion to ſeven, and alſo to eight.</hi> And verſ. 1. <hi>Caſt thy Bread upon the Waters, for thou ſhalt find it after many Dayes. The Bleſſings of him that was ready to periſh, come upon me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, Job</hi> 29.13. It was well for <hi>Dorcas,</hi> that the poor Widows could ſhew to <hi>Peter</hi> the Coats ſhe had made for them, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.39. <hi>Bleſſed is he that conſidereth the Poor, the Lord will deliver him in time of trouble, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 41.2, 3. <hi>He that hath pitty to the Poor, lendeth to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 19.17. <hi>And that which he hath given, will he pay him again;</hi> he ſhall be repaid with intereſt indeed: for it is a Sacrifice ſo acceptable, and well-pleaſing, that in return to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> who had ſent twice to <hi>Paul, even to</hi> Theſſalonica, <hi>to ſupply his neceſſity,</hi> Phil. 4.16. He ſaith, verſ. 19. <hi>My God ſhall ſupply all your need,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Lord ſhew mercy to the Houſe of</hi> Oniſiphorus, <hi>for he often refreſhed me, and was not aſhamed of my Chain,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>And whoſoever</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ſhall give to drink unto one of theſe little ones, a cup of cold Water onely, in the Name of a Diſciple, verily I ſay unto you, he ſhall in no wiſe loſe his reward,</hi> Mat. 10.42. For at the great day of Reckoning, the Lord will eſteem your Meat, Drink, Lodging, Clothing, and viſits of his Hungry, Thirſty, Pilgrim, Naked, Sick, and impriſoned Ones, as done to him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.35. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the contrary will be curſed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 41. <hi>For I was an Hungry, and ye gave me no Meat, &amp;c.</hi> But ſuch as conſider the Poor, are pronounced happy, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.21. <hi>He that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to the poor ſhall not lack, Prov.</hi> 28.27. and the <hi>Righteous doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them,</hi> Prov. 29.7. who yet perhaps, may need an exhortation to be more enquiring after thoſe that are at a diſtance from them in this evil day; and like the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ſhew more labour of love herein. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151855:4"/>making it more your buſineſs, as the Churches of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2, 3, 4. <hi>Who to their power, yea, and beyond their power</hi> (were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended herein) <hi>as willing;</hi> and according as the merciful Man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.5. ſo to order your affairs with diſcretion, as that you may be ever <hi>merciful and lending.</hi> Oh! how many a profuſe diſh of Meat, and other extravagancies, which (in ſuch times eſpecially) may be <hi>ſin</hi> to <hi>provide, &amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 22.13. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.4. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.10. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.20. might be profitably laid aſide for the poor? Oh! that we might not be by fits in this work, ſeeing the <hi>Poor</hi> are with us; and leſt, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.11. yea, increaſed daily, perhaps for tryal of our love unfeigned to the Lord a little ſeaſon, who will ſhortly rid them out of their diſtreſs; but that in giving, there might be a <hi>true reſpect</hi> unto their <hi>need, Deut.</hi> 15.8. <hi>He that hath a bountiful eye, ſhall be bleſſed; for he giveth of his bread to the poor, Prov.</hi> 22.9. As the good <hi>Samaritan, Luk.</hi> 10.33, 34, 35. who interrupted his Journey, imployed his Pains, Skill, Purſe, and Credit too, wholly to free the poor ſtranger out of his miſery, when the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Levite</hi> (that profeſſed more) neglected him: which <hi>pattern</hi> of <hi>pitty</hi> to our Neighbour, the Lord commendeth to us, <hi>verſ.</hi> 37. as our ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing example, when great Profeſſors fail: and himſelf our Pattern; who, <hi>though he was Rich, for our ſakes became Poor,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech you, put on <hi>bowels as the Elect of God;</hi> give not according to the broken fragments of money you have about you, but learn rather obedience to that Word of the Lord, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.33. <hi>Sell that you have, and give Alms.</hi> Oh! how far are rich Profeſſors from following the Lord herein, who among them hath voluntarily leſſened the yearly value of his Lands (in Obedience to the Lord of all) in this? Oh! that <hi>verſ.</hi> 34. may not conclude moſt rich Profeſſors Treaſure, to be onely earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>For where your Treaſure is, there will your hearts be alſo.</hi> But, alas! <hi>How dwelleth the Love of God in him who hath this Worlds goods, and ſeeth his Brother need, and ſhutteth up his Bowels of Compaſſion?</hi> Oh! tremble Rich Profeſſors, <hi>If</hi> (in your expence upon your ſelves) <hi>you are not ſo grieved for the afflictions of</hi> Joſeph, <hi>Amos</hi> 6.6. how can you face the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Word, in 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.17. with Peace, and ſhut up your Bowels to your poor Periſhing Brethren? Who ſhall truſt ſuch Stewards, with the true Riches, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.11. who deny the Lord, the faithful im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying the unrighteous <hi>Mammon?</hi> Profeſs what you will, you are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if you be ſo unnatural as not to bear the burthens of your diſtreſſed Brethren, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2, 3. Do you paſs on the other ſide, and hide your eyes like the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Levite,</hi> from the poor Object in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity? The compaſſionate <hi>Samaritan</hi> ſhall ſhame you in the Day of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you at ſuch a time (<hi>Dives</hi>-like) fare <hi>deliciouſly,</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151855:4"/>cloath your ſelf gorgiouſly, <hi>and ſtop your ears at the cry of the poor? you alſo ſhall cry your ſelves, and ſhall not be heard, Prov.</hi> 21.13. Yea, is it not come to paſs in part upon you already, as <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.13. (compared to <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.) for this very thing? And will not yet your danger be, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8.18? <hi>And though they cry in mine ears with a loud voice, yet will I not hear them. Is not this the faſt that I have choſen, to looſe the Bands of Wickedneſs; to undoe the heavy burthens, and to let the Oppreſſed go free? and that you break every Yoak? Is it not to deal thy Bread to the Hungry, and that thou bring the Poor that are caſt out to thy houſe? When thou ſeeſt the naked, that thou cover him, and that thou hide not thy ſelf from thine own fleſh; then ſhall thy light break forth, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa 58.6, 7, 8. <hi>Then ſhalt thou call, and the Lord will anſwer; thou ſhalt cry, and he will ſay, Here I am,</hi> verſ. 9. <hi>And if thou draw out thy Soul to the hungry, and ſatisfie the Afflicted Soul, then ſhall thy light riſe in obſecurity, and thy dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be as at noon-day: And the Lord ſhall guide thee continually, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie thy Soul in drought, &amp;c. verſ.</hi> 10, 11. But Oh rich Profeſſor! Canſt thou not draw out thy Soul? Canſt thou not ſell a part of thy Land, nor ſpare of thy Goods? Are thy Bowels ſo ſhut to thy poor Brother? Art thou rather aſhamed of him in his Bonds? Canſt thou not ſend to the Lord? Know then, <hi>Thou reproacheſt thy Maker, Prov.</hi> 14.31. He hath little credit with thee, while in this world; and thou ſhalt be reproached by him for ever, when he ſhall ſhut out thy cry. Oh! will thy fading Riches, whereof thou art an unjuſt Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, (<hi>Luke</hi> 16.9, 10, 11.) ſtand thee in ſtead with thy <hi>powerleſs Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> when he ſhall require of thee an <hi>account</hi> of thy <hi>Talent?</hi> and thou ſhalt appear before him on the left hand, to hear him indict thee on this wiſe, <hi>When I was an hungry,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.42, 43. But to ſuch as through Grace can <hi>truſt</hi> the Lord, and <hi>honour him with their Subſtance, Prov.</hi> 3.9. I hope I need now ſay no more then exhort you, <hi>to do it in ſimplicity,</hi> Rom. 12.8. <hi>according to your ability,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.11. <hi>chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> 2 Cor. 9.7. <hi>and as you have opportunity,</hi> Gal. 6.10. which will not be long. And whilſt the Lord, who giveth <hi>Seed to the Sower,</hi> and <hi>bleſſeth the Seed ſown,</hi> give you to <hi>reap bountifully,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. and <hi>bleſs</hi> your <hi>Seed ſown,</hi> to the bringing the Bleſſings of <hi>many that are ready to periſh upon you,</hi> and <hi>raiſing up</hi> in the heart of the relieved <hi>abundant thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving</hi> to God in your behalf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.12, 13. To that end, as you are intreated for the Lords ſake, to order your <hi>Affairs</hi> with <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all <hi>laviſh expenſes;</hi> every other way, to lay aſide to your <hi>utmoſt weekly,</hi> 1 Cor. 16.1, 2. and labour to engage <hi>(to this uſe)</hi> by your ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in treaty <hi>(like the Macedonians)</hi> ſome, as neat as you can, like <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.4. and <hi>Titus,</hi> verſ. 16. and ſuch <hi>whoſe praiſe is in the Goſpel,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151855:5"/>verſ. 18. and ſuch who have often times <hi>proved diligent in many things,</hi> but now are <hi>much more diligent,</hi> verſ. 22. whoſe <hi>work</hi> it may be more <hi>naturally to mind,</hi> and as <hi>equally</hi> as may be, adminiſter your liberality, to the neceſſity of the innumerable diſtreſſed; in wiſdom, that one do not abound, whilſt others periſh. Oh! that God would put it into the hearts of his Remnants every where, to imploy all their might herein; with <hi>correſpondency,</hi> like to the <hi>Body whereof Chriſt is the Head,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.26. 2 Cor. 11.29. That our <hi>Faſts</hi> may not be <hi>flung as dung in our Faces;</hi> but with our acceptable Alms, come before him; and that the <hi>Primitive Example</hi> aforeſaid, and the <hi>ſolemn chooſing ſeven men full of the Holy Spirit,</hi> in one <hi>Congregation, Acts</hi> 6.3, 7. might ſo far add to the weightineſs of this affair, that there might be at leaſt ſome ſuch ſet a part, on the behalf of the thouſands of Precious Ones, ready to periſh in the Land; that the fierce anger of the Lord may not yet further kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle upon us, to the curſing our Bleſſings, and we be extinct as Monſters, forgetting our own fleſh; that under ſo famous Profeſſion, and frequent and fervent Prayer, ſuffered our fellow Members to famiſh, whilſt we had fulneſs; Which the Lord in Mercy prevent. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And now a Word to the Afflicted.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN the time of adverſity conſider,</hi> is the Counſel given of the Lord, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.14. And indeed, till adverſity, we are like the <hi>Prodigal, Luke</hi> 15. who came not to himſelf, <hi>until he could not fill his belly with the Husks,</hi> verſ. 16. This Voice of the Lord calls now to the City, and the <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> will know <hi>his Name; hear the Rod, and who hath appointed it,</hi> Mich. 6.9. The <hi>Viſitations</hi> of the Lord preſerved <hi>Jobs</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Job</hi> 10.12. and if that be not the <hi>Fruit,</hi> to <hi>take away the ſin,</hi> Iſa. 27.9. there is too much cauſe to fear, whether ſuch a Profeſſors Caſe be compriſed in the <hi>New Covenant, Pſalm.</hi> 89.32. and then his <hi>Poverty,</hi> and his <hi>Riches,</hi> his <hi>Priſon,</hi> and his <hi>Liberty,</hi> will be much a like, <hi>under a Curſe;</hi> and he will fall into the two extream evils which <hi>Agar</hi> prayed (and <hi>Solomon</hi> by the Spirit gave Counſel) againſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.11. But if the Lord pleaſe, I would (<hi>Elihu</hi>-like) ſpeak in the <hi>uprightneſs</hi> of my <hi>heart, and utter knowledge clearly herein,</hi> Job 33.3.</p>
               <p>I am very much perſwaded, <hi>That the good Figs for their good, are come firſt into captivity,</hi> Jer. 2.4, 5. By captivity I mean the variety of cloſe affliction, which the Lord immediately, or by cruel men, or any other way, hath brought them into, or bound them with, and by which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151855:5"/>he hath brought them down <hi>wonderfully;</hi> for ſo <hi>Job</hi>'s <hi>various diſtreſſe</hi> is called a <hi>Captivity, Job</hi> 42.10. And now, whether Poor, in Priſon, or both Robbed, Spoiled, or on the Bed of Sickneſs; Baniſhed or chaſed from thy dwelling, with the addition too (it may be) of inward with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I deſire that firſt of all, I may be accepted in imploring thy very ſerious and diligent ſearch, and ſelf-examination, with aſſurance, that, that word, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.23. is as true in thy caſe as ever, <hi>That God hath not done without cauſe, all that he hath done unto thee;</hi> and that (ſtill finding out the cauſe) there will be no diſpoſition to returning, but to ſelf-juſtifying ſtill, as <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8, 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Till then the Commiſſion for outward Judgements may continue, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.40. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.9. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Inſenſibleneſs of the Cauſe, expoſeth to filthy-fretting, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.23, 24. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.3. but <hi>Aaron,</hi> when the <hi>Cauſe</hi> was ſhewed him, held his <hi>peace, Lev.</hi> 10.3. and ſo <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Till then, we cannot ſo fitly enjoy deliverance, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.63. &amp; 36.31, 32.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> This is a mean to deliver, when nothing elſe will do, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.9, 10, 15. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.1. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Hereby God will be honoured again, and his Name glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly vindicated, when thou ſhalt ſeriouſly thus acknowledge thy offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.19. And for Helps herein, I beſeech you,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Hearken to the voice of the preſent Rod, expounded by the Word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.25. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.3 <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.4. <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.25. <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let no ſpecial excellency cauſe thee to over-look the Cauſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4, 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.20. much leſs when it may be with thee, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Eli, Moſes, Jehoſhaphat, Hezekiah, Aſa, Jonah, David,</hi> &amp;c. troubled themſelves, and ſome of them <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though they were emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Begin at the Root, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.2. to. 15. &amp; <hi>verſ.</hi> 27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Do not clear thy ſelf, becauſe men may in many things falſly accuſe thee, <hi>Job</hi> 40.2. <hi>to</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 42.1, 2. nor becauſe men may in every thing commend thee, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.4. But,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Above all, ſeek at the Throne earneſtly, with a true diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to return, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.40, 41. <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.12, 13, 14.</p>
               <p>Know now aſſuredly, that the Priſon or Captivity in which thou art, is God's <hi>School</hi> or <hi>Univerſity,</hi> wherein he would ſhew thee thy <hi>work,</hi> and the <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> wherein thou haſt exceeded, <hi>Job</hi> 36.8, 9. — For thy work then, ſure if thou art choſen to bear his Name, it is ſet down briefly in this ſingle Scripture, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.8. and <hi>what doth the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151855:6"/>quire of thee? but to do juſtly, to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God.</hi> Whereon I will not inlarge impertinently, to ſwell my ſpeech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the patience of the afflicted, which perhaps his tribulation yet hath nor effected; but <hi>expound,</hi> walking humbly with thy God, by that <hi>explanation</hi> in <hi>James</hi> 4.7. where it is called, <hi>a ſubmitting unto God,</hi> that is, <hi>to his Counſel,</hi> to his <hi>Will,</hi> with a <hi>reverend reſpect</hi> to all his <hi>advice</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> therein; contented with our condition, <hi>turning</hi> to his Will, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and timely under his reproof. Now poor Soul, was there not a day wherein Profeſſors experienced happineſs, whilſt they walked ſo humbly with their God? contented with Food &amp; Rayment in the Work and Way of God? living in the comfort of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt? in rich communion with him? innocently abiding with him, as in the <hi>Caſe of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulam,</hi> for his will and work? cleaving to ſuch as <hi>favoured his Righteous Cauſe in truth?</hi> and ſteering thy courſe by the ſtreight Rule of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel; not loving thy life in compariſon of his Precious Service, Cauſe and Goſpel? and <hi>whether it was not then better with thee?</hi> Did not all them that devoured thee offend? <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Doſt thou no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> yet ſay, It was then bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with me then now? Hoſ.</hi> 2.7. Doſt not yet hear the Lord lamenting over thee? as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.11. to 15. <hi>Oh that my people had hearkened to me, &amp;c.</hi> Doſt not yet know it's befallen thee, as <hi>Ephraim? Hoſ.</hi> 13.1, 9. Canſt thou not <hi>remember</hi> where thou didſt <hi>loſe</hi> thy <hi>Crown?</hi> that the way in which <hi>Ephraim got gray hairs,</hi> Hoſ. 7.8. <hi>to the end,</hi> ſtole inſenſibly upon thee? &amp; when men <hi>gathered thee? John</hi> 15.6. when the <hi>preſent world was imbraced?</hi> 2 Tim. 4.10. Was there not a time wherein thou <hi>followedſt God, as in a Land which was not ſown?</hi> Jer. 2.2. and thoughtſt thou hadſt <hi>gain</hi> enough <hi>in God and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs?</hi> 1 Tim. 6.6. and thoughtſt thou hadſt enough of the world, and couldſt never get enough of God? and hath not a time ſtolen upon thee, wherein thou couldeſt never get enough of this world, but hadſt enough of God? When thou turnedſt thy back upon the <hi>ſuccesful victorious way of Faith,</hi> and tryedſt the Carnal way of ſence (<hi>like the Nations,</hi> Jer. 2.31.) in Pride and Oppreſſion <hi>ſtaying thereon?</hi> Iſa. 30.12, 13, 14. when the Word of the Lord <hi>grew a burthen to thee?</hi> Jer. 6.10, 11. when thou greweſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for thy utmoſt portion of earthly things, and cold and indifferent in heavenly things? Then thou mayeſt partly ſee thy work, and the <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion</hi> thou haſt exceeded. Haſt thou not in thy fulneſs alſo fallen into <hi>Sodoms</hi> ſnare? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.49. Pride, fulneſs of bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and been proud alſo of the <hi>Mountain</hi> or <hi>Temple of the Lord,</hi> Jer. 7.4. under even the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions tranſgreſſions? Was zeal for Righteouſneſs, and ſence of others cry in ſimplicity of Soul, turned into inſenſibleneſs of others ſufferings, and ſatisfaction taken in ſelf, ſenſuality? then mayſt thou cry <hi>(for a ſeaſon at leaſt)</hi> and not be heard, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.13. Was ſucceſſes abuſed, to <hi>advance thy</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in provoking
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151855:6"/>the Lord to <hi>jealouſly?</hi> Deut. 32.6. by lightneſs in Worſhip, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.22. by breaking faith with the Enemy, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1, 2, 3. and oppreſſing thy Brethren too at the ſame time, thinking to <hi>build Zion with blood,</hi> Mich. 3.10, 11. (wherefore it is now <hi>plowed as a field,</hi> &amp;c.) and to <hi>ſettle on the lees,</hi> Zeph. 1.12, 13. when thou hadſt gotten greatneſs and lands, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.11, 12. bleſſing thoſe that ſo ſteered backward, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 10.3. or at leaſt not mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning over theſe, and ſuch like departings and evils, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.4. then is our work now beſt to be, as <hi>Eze.</hi> 7.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.12. <hi>Ezr.</hi> 10.6. &amp; to come to the Valley of <hi>Achor,</hi> ſtoning in our ſelves and others theſe troubling <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions;</hi> and to be humbled deeply, if the Lord ſeem to give us a divorce, as <hi>Jer.</hi> 11.15. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.15. And if any of you have got riches, &amp; not by right, and now leave them in the midſt of your dayes; or if you with-held, and it tendeth to <hi>penury, lay your hand on your mouth,</hi> Jer. 17.11. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.24. if by any hint thou ſeeſt thy ſickneſs, and thy wound, do not do now as <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 57.9. but try the <hi>good old way</hi> following, wherein never any yet fail'd of finding effect, who attained to it in truth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.29. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.1. &amp; 14.2, 3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3, 4. &amp; 31.18, 19, 20. <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.2. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.16. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord God, the Holy One of Iſrael, In returning and reſt ſhall ye be ſaved; in quietneſs and in confidence ſhall be your ſtrength, and ye would not; but ye ſaid, no; for we will flee upon Horſes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.15. But you will ſay to me, Who is he that liveth and ſinneth not? have not all their faults? yea, yet let me ſay to thee, the <hi>ſpots</hi> of the Lords <hi>people</hi> are of ſeveral <hi>ſorts;</hi> and though all of them have ſinned, it is not ſafe (like the Hypocrite or time-ſerver) to quit ſcores; therefore with their reprovers to ſpare the troubling ſin. All <hi>Iſrael</hi> had ſin in them, but <hi>Achans</hi> eſpecially troubled <hi>Iſrael;</hi> therefore your Generation-ſin againſt Gods Holy and Righteous Cauſe in your hands, diſhonouring it, and his Holy Name, either by Oppreſſion, graſping after the worlds greatneſs, wiſdom or riches: which was ſo weak before you, unbelief drawing back, bringing an evil report upon the Promiſes; not delighting in, but deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the good Word and Wayes of the Lord; truſting in an Arm of fleſh; lightly breaking Vows, and Faith, with God and men; walking haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and loftily, whilſt oppreſſion and violence continued and increaſed. Yea laſtly, making Covenants with Hell and Death, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.18. that is, Carnal intereſts, for fear of danger; ſaying, The time is not yet, <hi>and the Lord will neither do good nor evil, Zeph.</hi> 1.12. and the like, are in the firſt place to be made cloſe inquiry after, as troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and cauſers of confuſion. Yet alſo have thoſe that have erred in viſion, and ſtaggered in judgement, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.7. limitting the Holy One to times, inſtruments and wayes of working, either for his People, or againſt his Adverſaries, which he removeth as he ſees good, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.50. though they ſhould be wholly free (through mercy) from that dethroning ſin of making league
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151855:7"/>with curſed intereſts, through unbelief, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. yet have they much cauſe of mourning, as having ſinned both towards God greatly, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned ſtumbling to many, and to their own Souls. Yea, laſtly, If God hath given ſo much integrity to any, as to preſerve them from the raging power of all the firſt black claſſes of publick corruptions (which is much to be feared) yet if thou haſt been proud of thine integrity, as <hi>Job</hi> 32.9. <hi>ſlighty</hi> in thy reproofs, as <hi>Eli,</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.14. exalting thy ſelf as <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Muſt we fetch water,</hi> Num. 20.10. inſtead of ſanctifying God; Yea, in the oſtentation of <hi>Hezekiah, Iſ.</hi> 39.2. may not God bring thee through <hi>Jobs</hi> furnace, to bring thee into his abaſement, <hi>Job</hi> 42.6. or make thy ears tingle as <hi>Eli</hi> with rebukes, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.13. or bury thee in ſilence as <hi>Moſes, Num.</hi> 34.5, 6. or make all that is in thy houſe be carried into captivity, as <hi>Hezekiah, Iſa.</hi> 39.6. but eſpecially, if <hi>Cain</hi>-like, thou haſt been glad in uncovering the nakedneſs of others; or <hi>Herod,</hi> or <hi>Jehu</hi>-like haſt affected praiſe, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 12.23. or to have thy name exalted; may not God pour contempt upon thee? Oh! that we might be united in abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, through the pouring down of the Spirit of Grace and ſupplication, as <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10, 11, 13. Obſerve theſe, that the houſe of <hi>Levi, Nathan</hi> and <hi>David</hi> (which were moſt eminent for faithfulneſs to the Lord) ſhall yet ſee cauſe enough (for their ſhortneſs made known to them in the light of the Spirit) to mourn as deeply (it may be) as <hi>Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mei,</hi> who at firſt curſed the work of God, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.5. Yea truly, the <hi>Publican</hi>-like defiled One, or who may be too juſtly ſtiled the Apoſtate (that ſaid, <hi>I will not,</hi> and after repented and went, <hi>Lu.</hi> 21.19.) ſhall be before many that have learned to ſay, <hi>Apoſtate</hi> at every word, and walk not humbly with their God. On therefore! that as there may be maintained an irreconcilable enmity to, and true mourning over, yea conſtant, ſeaſonable reprehenſion of every of the aforeſaid evils; ſo alſo we might be more in the Spirit of the Holy Reprover of Old, and in their humility for our ſhare of the evil, and ſhortneſs to prevent or cure it; which beſides their own inward corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhamed them alwayes before the Lord; and though kept (through grace) from the publick groſs appearances of defilements in their day, yet involved themſelves in their confeſſions uſually with the worſt of the Tranſgreſſors, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.7. <hi>Ne.</hi> 9.33, 34. <hi>Da.</hi> 9.5. to 10, 13, 14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.16. <hi>and</hi> 6.5. Oh! how humbly do the Holy Angels appear in the perfect Will of God? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.2. The ſnuffers of the Sanctuary, were to be of pure gold, <hi>Exod.</hi> 37.23. What need have brazen reprovers to bluſh then before the Lord? and deſire rather the power of Chriſt, then pride of their own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity might reſt upon them. The great means then that I adviſe towards thee, through healing of the breach (this day upon the Lords poor Ones) is, true poverty of Spirit; each bearing his ſhame, unto through abaſement and repentance never to be repented of; no man ſparing his own, nor
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151855:7"/>comming into the ſecret of any who would have his name whole, and his ſin ſpared; but that they may be united indeed, thus to joyn together, to make one head, as <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.11. to look on their ſin-wildred-ſtate, and ſean no more to their own <hi>underſtanding,</hi> but upon their Beloved; (as to truſt in his Words, ſo to wait for and walk in his way) And then I aſſure you, He that ſittern upon the Throne, would ſoon <hi>make all things new,</hi> Rev. 21.5. <hi>A new ſharp threſhing Inſtrument, having teeth,</hi> ſhall quickly be intruſted unto them who would imploy it with ſtrength, chiefly. Firſt, Againſt their own abhominations; then ſhal <hi>the iniquity of</hi> Iſrael <hi>be ſought for, and there ſhall be none, and the ſins of</hi> Judah, <hi>and they ſhall not be found; For I will pardon them whom I reſerve,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.20. <hi>In one day the inquity of that Land ſhould be removed,</hi> Zech. 3.9. and the Lord their God ſhall ſave them in that day, as the <hi>flock of his People; for, they ſhall be as the ſtones of a Crown lifted up, as an enſign upon his Land. O turn you to the ſtrong hold ye Priſoners of hope, even to day do I declare, I will render dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thee,</hi> Zech. 9.12, 16. <hi>For in this Mountain ſhall the Hand of the Lord reſt,</hi> (that is his contending hand, with his inheritance) <hi>and</hi> Moab <hi>ſhall be troden down under him, even as ſtraw is trodden down for the Dunghil,</hi> Iſa. 25.10. <hi>In that day ſhall this Song be ſung in the Land of</hi> Judah, <hi>We have a ſtrong City, Salvation will God appoint for Walls and Bulwarks,</hi> Iſa. 26.1. <hi>There will I make the horn of</hi> David <hi>to bud. His Foundation is in the Holy Mountains; for thus hath the Lord ſpoken unto me, like as the Lyon, and the young Lyon roaring on his prey; when a multitude of Shepherds are called forth againſt him, he will not be afraid of their voice, nor abaſe himſelf for the noiſe of them; ſo ſhall the Lord of Hoſts come down to fight for Mount</hi> Zion, <hi>and for the hill thereof. As Birds flying, ſo will the Lord of Hoſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>defending alſo, he will deliver it, and paſſing over, he will preſerve it,</hi> Pſal. 132.17. &amp; 87.1. <hi>Turn ye unto him from whom the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>have deeply revolted,</hi> Iſa. 31.4, 5, 6. <hi>Therefore will he give them up, until the time that ſhe which travaileth hath brought forth; Then the remnant of his Brethren ſhall return unto the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and he ſhall ſtand and feed in the ſtrength of the Lord, in the Majeſty of the Name of the Lord his God, and they ſhall abide; for now ſhall he be great unto the ends of the earth,</hi> Mich. 5.3, 4. <hi>Be in pain</hi> therefore, <hi>and labour to bring forth, O Daughter of</hi> Zion, <hi>like a woman in travel; for now thou ſhalt go forth out of the City, and thou ſhalt dwell in the field, and thou ſhalt go even to</hi> Babylon, <hi>there ſhalt thou be delivered; There the Lord ſhall redeem thee from the hand of thine enemies,</hi> Mich. 4.10. <hi>The foot ſhall tread it down, even the feet of the poor, and ſteps of the needy,</hi> Iſa. 26.6. For <hi>he will regard the prayer of the deſtitute, and not deſpiſe their Prayer,</hi> Pſal. 102.17. <hi>This ſhall be written for the Generations to come, and the people which ſhall be created, ſhall praiſe the Name of the Lord; for he looked down from the height of his Sanctuary
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151855:8"/>from Heaven did the Lord behold the Earth, to hear the groaning of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, to looſe thoſe that are appointed to death, to declare the Name of the Lord in</hi> Zion, <hi>and his praiſe in</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>when the people are gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and the Kingdoms to ſerve the Lord. For the Lord ſhall Judge his people, and repent himſelf for his Servants; when he ſeeth that their power is gone, and there is none ſhut up or left,</hi> Deut. 32.36. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Even ſo come Lord Jeſus, come quickly. <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>But a Word to their Oppreſſors.</head>
               <p>TO deliver mine own Soul, yet cautiouſly, for ſome of them are now grown ſuch ſons of <hi>Belial, that a man cannot ſpeak to them,</hi> 1 Sam. 25.17. and therefore I will confine my ſelf to ſome Scripture truths (not yet out of date) which it wil concern them to conſider, as the <hi>Oracles</hi> of him who (if they will not hear) ſhall make himſelf be heard, by another voice of his, that yet they have not heard. <hi>And the Lord ſhall cauſe his glorious Voice to be heard, &amp; ſhal ſhew the lightning down of his Arm, with the indignation of his Anger, and with the flame of a devouring Fire: with ſcattering, and tempeſt, and hail-ſtones; for through the Voice of the Lord, ſhall the</hi> Aſſyrian <hi>be beaten down, which ſmote with a Rod,</hi> Iſa. 30.30, 31. <hi>And I will execute vengeance in anger, and fury upon the</hi> Heathen, <hi>ſuch as they have not heard,</hi> Mich. 5.15. <hi>The great day of the Lord is near, it is near, and haſteth greatly, even the Voice of the Day of the Lord; the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty man ſhall cry there bitterly,</hi> Zeph. 1.8. to 18. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord God, My people went down aforetime into</hi> Egypt <hi>to ſojourn there, and the</hi> Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian <hi>oppreſſed them without cauſe; Now therefore, what have I here, ſaith the Lord, that my people is taken away? They that rule over them, make them to howl, ſaith the Lord, and my Name continually every day is blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed; therefore my people ſhall know my Name, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 52.4, 5, 6. <hi>So that a man ſhall ſay; Verily there is a reward for the Righteous; verily there is a God that judgeth in the Earth,</hi> Pſal. 58.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wo to the bloody City, it is full of lies, the prey departeth not; Art thou better than populous No,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>All thy ſtrong holds ſhall be like fig-trees, with the firſt ripe figs; if they be ſhaken, they ſhall even fall into the mouth of the eater. Thy crowned men are as the Locuſts, and thy Captains as the great graſs-hoppers, which camp in the hedges in the cold day, but when the Sun ariſeth they flee away, and their place is not known where they are. There is no healing of thy bruiſe, thy wound is grievous, all that hear the bruit of thee, ſhall clap their hands over thee; for upon whom hath not thy wickedneſs paſſed continually?</hi> Nahum 3.1. <hi>She is empty, and void, and waſte; and the heart melteth, and the knees ſmite together,</hi> Nahum 1.10. <hi>Becauſe ye
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151855:8"/>were glad, becauſe ye rejoyced, O ye deſtroyers of my heritage.</hi>—Jer. 50.11. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord God, Becauſe thou haſt clapped thy hands, and ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with thy feet, and rejoyced in heart with all thy deſpite againſt the Land of</hi> Iſrael, Ezek. 25.6. <hi>And have taken vengeance with a deſpiteful heart to deſtroy it, for the old hatred,</hi> verſ. 15. <hi>Behold I will make</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>a cup of trembling unto all people round about, when they ſhall be in the ſiege both againſt</hi> Judah <hi>and againſt</hi> Jeruſalem. <hi>And in that day, I will make</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem <hi>a burthenſome ſtone for all people; all that burthen themſelves with it, ſhall be cut in pieces. Though all the people of the earth be gathered together againſt it; In that day, ſaith the Lord, I will ſmite every horſe with aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and his rider with madneſs, and I will open mine eyes upon the houſe of</hi> Judah, &amp;c. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.2, 3, 4. <hi>The adverſaries of the Lord ſhall be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to pieces, out of Heaven ſhall he thunder upon them; the Lord will judge the ends of the Earth, and he ſhall give ſtrength unto his King, and exalt the horn of his Anointed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.10. <hi>Moreover, the multitude of thy ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſhall be like the ſmall duſt, and the multitude of the terrible ones ſhall be as chaff that paſſeth away; Yea, it ſhall be at an inſtant ſuddenly. Thou ſhalt be viſited of the Lord of Hoſts, with thunder and with earth-quake, and great noiſe; with ſtorm and tempeſt, and the flame of devouring fire. And the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of all the Nations, that fight againſt</hi> Ariel, <hi>even all that fight againſt her, and her munition, and that diſtreſs her, ſhall be as a dream of a night viſion,</hi> Iſa. 29.5, 6, 7. <hi>I was wroth with my People, I have polluted mine inheritance, and given them into thine hand; thou didſt ſhew them no mercy: upon the Ancients haſt thou very heavily laid the Yoak,</hi> Iſa. 47.6, 11. <hi>And thou ſaidſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore ſhall evil come upon thee, thou ſhalt not know from whence it riſeth; and miſchief ſhall fall upon thee, thou ſhalt not be able to put it off; and deſolation ſhall come upon thee ſuddenly, which thou ſhalt not know.</hi> And verſ. 3. <hi>I will take vengeance, I will not meet thee as a man; for he bringeth down them that dwell on high, the lofty City he layeth it low, he layeth it low, even to the ground, he bringeth it even to the duſt: The foot ſhall tread it down, even the foot of the poor, and the ſteps of the needy,</hi> Iſa. 26.5, 6. <hi>Let favour be ſhewed to the wicked, yet will he not learn Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: In the land of uprightneſs will he deal unjuſtly; and will not behold the Majeſty of the Lord. Lord, when thy hand is lifted up, they will not ſee; but they ſhall ſee, and be aſhamed for their envie at thy people; yea, the fire of thine enemy ſhall devour them. And they ſhall paſs through it hardly beſted and hungry; and it ſhall come to paſs, that when they ſhall be hungry, they ſhall fret themſelves, and curſe their King and their God, and look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: and they ſhall look to the earth, and behold trouble and darkneſs, dimneſs of anguiſh, and they ſhall be driven to darkneſs,</hi> Iſa. 8.21, 22. <hi>Behold the whirlwind of the Lord goeth forth with fury, a continual whirlwind, it ſhall fall with pain upon the head of the wicked; the fierce anger of the Lord
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151855:9"/>ſhall not return, until he hath done it, and until he hath performed the intents of his heart; in the latter dayes you ſhall conſider it,</hi> Jer. 30.23, 24. <hi>For the Lord ſhall riſe up as in Mount</hi> Perazim; <hi>he ſhall be wroth as in the valley of</hi> Gibeon, <hi>that he may do his work, his ſtrange work; and bring to paſs his Act, his ſtrange Act: Now therefore be ye not mockers, leſt your bonds be made ſtrong,</hi> Iſa. 28.21, 22. <hi>Beware therefore, leſt that come upon you, which is ſpoken of in the Prophets; Behold ye deſpiſers, and wonder, and periſh; for I work a work in your dayes, a work which ye ſhall in no wiſe believe, though a man declare it unto you,</hi> Acts 13.40, 41. <hi>And that prophane wicked Prince of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>whoſe day is come, when Iniquity ſhall have an end; Thus ſaith the Lord God, Remove the Diadem, and take off the CRown, this ſhall not be the ſame; exalt him that is low, and abaſe him that is high. I will overturn, overturn, overturn it, and it ſhall be no more, until He come whoſe right it is, and I will give it Him,</hi> Ezek. 31.25, 26, 27. <hi>His enemies will I cloath with ſhame, but on himſelf ſhall his Crown flouriſh,</hi> Pſal. 132.18. <hi>And he ſhall come upon Princes, as upon Morter, and as the Potter treadeth clay,</hi> Iſa. 41.25. <hi>For the oppreſſion of the poor, and ſighing of the needy; now will I ariſe (ſaith the Lord) I will ſet him in ſafety from him that puffeth at him,</hi> Pſal. 12.5. <hi>The meek alſo ſhall increaſe their joy in the Lord, and the poor among men ſhall rejoyce in the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael: <hi>for the terrible one is brought to nought, and the ſcorner is conſumed; and all that watch for iniquity are cut off; that make a man an offender for a word, and lay a ſnare for him that reproveth in the gate; and turn a ſide the juſt for a thing of nought,</hi> Iſa. 29.19, 20, 21. Ezek. 35.5. Jer. 46.17. Iſa. 10.1, 4. Ezek. 29.7. <hi>Be wiſe now therefore O ye Kings; be inſtructed ye Judges of the Earth; ſerve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling. Kiſs the Son leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little. Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in Him,</hi> Pſal. 2.10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Have all the workers of Iniquity no knowledge? who eat up my people as they eat bread, and call not upon the Lord. There were they in great fear: for God is in the Generation of the Righteous,</hi> Pſalm. 14.4, 5.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
